now let's continue with task four here in the
same way as in the last task we have to take our
image from last week the little tree and
add an animation to it and the whole thing
should look something like this there's this tree
and it shakes like it's hit by some
wind and then importantly it stops
okay so I went ahead and filled
the basic structure in from
our solution for last week's
task so we have our tree
here just stands there does nothing so now we have
to do something with this t parameter again and
the first thing I would do is again introduce a
where block with some offset which I initially
define to be t and then I basically just say okay
let's just start by translating
the crown by some offset because
this is what it looks like here
the crown kind of moves to the right
to the left so let's start with that
let's have a look at this
what does this actually do obviously not the right
thing but it's a good start so it starts moving
but it doesn't come back so
how do we fix this? well here we can use the
sine function to add a kind of boundary to the
left and the right of this movement because
it will now oscillate between left and right
movement and this looks kind of
like the shaking we are aiming for
but it's way too far to the right and the left so
let's dampen this a little bit by adding a factor
so now the distance from the center of the
tree is not so big anymore and it looks
almost like the one here
if we squint a little bit
but it doesn't stop it keeps
going and going so at some point
we need to make sure it stops so I'm introducing
a conditional that says as long as t is let's say
below
1.5 times pi which is
three iterations so we first uh move to the
left then to the right then to the left and
then to the right again then if we are below this
threshold we use this sine as the offset and else
we use a zero offset meaning we stop
moving so let's have a look at this
so now to the left and one more to the right
oh no it's just this case just to the left to
the right and then there's some jump because
I intended to speed this actually
up by multiplying the t in the sine
parameter
and then our boundary works out okay
so this is the crown moving now what about the
branches let's see the branches have to definitely
not just shift left and right they have to rotate
kind of so let's try that let's just say we had
rotated the branches and let's use the offset,
for instance, let's just see what happens
okay it looks kind of strange
maybe we should use the
offset to actually rotate in the other direction
okay this looks better but still kind of
strange because well you would assume the
branches rotate around this spot when actually
they rotate around this spot somewhere here
and this is because in CodeWorld
we have this problem with rotation
and translation because rotation is always
rotating around the center of some image
you have the property that to
translate an image from x and y after
rotating it by some
angle the picture is p here
this is not the same as
doing it the other way around
so this is important to keep in
mind because it means that we
need to actually in order to rotate these
things correctly we need to do the rotation
further inside the branch picture so what we do is
we add an additional parameter to branches: offset
and now branches takes a Double named offset
and now in this we could add this here to where
we rotated the branches to kind of go in these two
directions we say okay let's add the offset here
see what happens; because we now move them over
this translated here which makes a difference
so what do we end up with now? oh well it's
gotten worse hmm what's the problem now?
well now you can see that it actually the
branches rotate around this specific position
right? because we got rid of the
extra wobbling introduced by this translated
primitive so to speak when we still have
the center of the newly created
rectangles here if you look at this
these are the branches if we look
at a single branch that we rotate
we start with a solid rectangle and when we
rotate it we rotate it around the middle but we
would like to rotate it around the place where
it attaches to the trunk so how do we do this?
we add another translated
primitive translated and we
raise the branch by half of its height
so this means that now the
bottom end of the branch is at
the origin of the coordinate plane
and this means we rotate around this point then so
let's see if it actually works obviously we have
to do some additional adjustment now but the basic
principle works because if we inspect this now
we have the solid rectangle it's
translated up by 1 then it's colored brown
rotated around the origin point
then translated upwards but this
upwards translation is now wrong because we
introduced this additional translation here so
let's get rid of this so we no longer
need to translate this branch to the left
and this branch to the right so now they meet
in the middle obviously this translated 0 0 is
meaningless at the moment but we needed to
push the branches back down a bit so to speak
so now we just introduce some additional
offset here like -1.7 something like this
no, not 1.7
0.75 is what I wanted to go
for, was it? yeah kind of
okay now the last thing:
our rotation is still in the wrong
direction so I need to change the
sign of the offset here which I forgot to
do previously but then looks okay so now
what we can realize is that if you look at this
expression we're just getting kind of
long let's break this into two lines
so now these two look quite similar
especially the first part here so
we could definitely just take this
and factor it outside of this
so we put this here and then do
kind of like this
okay so we got rid of one translated call here but
if we look even more carefully you can see that
the first thing we do with these branches out here
is to translate them so you can even take this
and basically pull it out here which then we can
combine by saying okay let's just
subtract 0.75 from 2.5 so we have 1.75
and now we have our final animation
it stops at some point and we even
cleaned up our code a little bit
okay I think one of the main take-home messages here
is to always keep in mind that this is not a valid
equality but rather an inequality in CodeWorld
so if you have rotation and translation combined
always keep an eye out to do them in the right
order otherwise you get strange animations